A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Board of Fisheries Records, 1898-1927
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Board of Fisheries Records, 1898-1927
The Library of Virginia
APA 113, APA 114, APA 115
57 volumes
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
On 25 March 1875 the General Assembly authorized the governor to appoint three commissioners of fisheries to coordinate conservation activities with the federal government and to oversee the duties of local oyster inspectors. The number of commissioners was reduced to one by an act passed on 8 March 1877. The Office of Fish Commissioner was abolished by the General Assembly on 7 February 1898 and replaced by the Board of Fisheries. The board also assumed the functions of the Board on the Chesapeake and Its Tributaries.
On 5 February 1900 the General Assembly passed an act authorizing the Board of Fisheries to employ county surveyors to resurvey the oyster planting grounds and any part of the survey made in the 1890s by James B. Baylor that needed revision. On 12 Mar 1908 the General Assembly changed the name of board to the Commission on Fisheries. In 1968 the name of the commission was changed to the Marine Resources Commission.
Scope and Content
The Board of Fisheries records include Horizontal Angle Books, 1901; Oyster Reports, 1898-1927; and Reports of Oyster Inspectors, 1898-1927. These records document surveys of oyster beds in Isle of Wight County, and the collection of fines, fees, and taxes by Inspectors of Oysters.
Counties covered in these records include: Accomack, Charles City, Elizabeth City, Essex, Gloucester, Isle of Wight, James City, King and Queen, King George, King William, Lancaster, Mathews, Middlesex, Nansemond, New Kent, Norfolk, Northumberland, Princess Anne, Richmond, Stafford, Warwick, Westmoreland and York, as well as Norfolk City and Portsmouth.
The records are arranged into 3 series. This collection consists of several Auditor of Public Accounts (APA) accessions that, while identified separately, all pertain to the same category of records. Since the specific APA accession numbers have been used and referenced over the years it was decided that each series would reference it's specific APA number, but one finding aid would describe the entire collection.
Arrangement
Series I: Horizontal Angle Books, 1901 (APA 113)
Series II: Oyster Reports, 1898-1927 (APA 114)
Series III: Reports of Oyster Inspectors, 1898-1927 (APA 115)
Contents List
- Series I: Horizontal Angle Books, 1901 (APA 113)., Extent: 8 volumes. (Volume 1-8)
  Horizontal Angle Books, 1901, consist of 8 volumes and contain notes concerning surveys of oyster beds in the James River in Isle of Wight County that were created in conjuction with the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey. The observations of P.C. Warwick, Jr. are mostly related to surveying measurements, but occasionally plats and diagrams are recorded.
  Arranged chronoloically.
  - James River, 1901. (Volume 1)
  - Isle of Wight, 1901. (Volume 2)
  - James River - Jones and Pagan Creeks, 1901. (Volume 3)
  - Isle of Wight, 1901. (Volume 4)
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey - James River / Pagan Creek, 1901. (Volume 5)
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey - Isle of Wight, 1901. (Volume 6)
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey - Isle of Wight, 1901. (Volume 7)
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey - Isle of Wight, 1901. (Volume 8)
- Series II: Oyster Reports, 1898-1927 (APA 114)., Extent: 38 volumes. (Box 1-38)
  Oyster Reports, 1898-1927, consist of 38 volumes and include information of fees, fines, rents and taxes collected by Inspectors of Oysters. These reports cover the years 1898-1904 and 1920-1927. Volume numbers were supplied at the time of processing.
  The 1860 Code of Virginia authorized county courts to appoint inspectors of oysters to enforce oyster laws and collect fines and fees. The General Assembly passed an act on 3 March 1866 amending the code's provisions and requiring the oyster inspectors to report their collection periodically to the auditor of public accounts. Although it was revised several times, the system remained in place until the office of the auditor was abolished in 1928.
  These monthly reports to the Board of Fisheries and Auditor of Public Accounts contain the name and residence of each person paying the fine, fee, rent or tax, the location and assessed value of the oyster ground, and the type, amount and date of payment. May also include information boat registration, tongs registered and oysters sold, and later volumes include information on crabbing, clamming, and fishing/nets.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Accomack-King and Queen, 1898. (Volume 1)
  - Lancaster-York, 1898. (Volume 2)
  - Accomack-Gloucester, 1899. (Volume 3)
  - Isle of Wight-Middlesex, 1899. (Volume 4)
  - Nansemond-York, 1899. (Volume 5)
  - Accomack-Gloucester, 1900. (Volume 6)
  - Isle of Wight-Nansemond, 1900. (Volume 7)
  - New Kent-York, 1900. (Volume 8)
  - Accomack-Lancaster, 1901 Jan-June. (Volume 9)
  - Mathews-York, 1901 Jan-June. (Volume 10)
  - Accomack-York, 1901 July-Dec. (Volume 11)
  - Accomack-York, 1902 Jan-Apr. (Volume 12)
  - Accomack-York, 1902 May-Aug. (Volume 13)
  - Accomack-York, 1902 Aug-Dec. (Volume 14)
  - Accomack-York, 1903 Jan-May. (Volume 15)
  - Accomack-York, 1903 June-Sept. (Volume 16)
  - Accomack-York, 1903 Oct-1904 Mar. (Volume 17)
  - Accomack-York, 1904 Apr-Sept. (Volume 18)
  - Accomack-York, 1920 Mar-Apr. (Volume 19)
  - Accomack-York, 1920 May-Aug. (Volume 20)
  - Accomack-York, 1920 Sept-1921 Feb. (Volume 21)
  - Accomack-York, 1921 Mar-Aug. (Volume 22)
  - Accomack-York, 1921 Sept-1922 Feb. (Volume 23)
  - Accomack-York, 1922 Mar-Aug. (Volume 24)
  - Accomack-York, 1922 Sept-Dec. (Volume 25)
  - Accomack-York, 1923 Jan-Apr. (Volume 26)
  - Accomack-York, 1923 May-Aug. (Volume 27)
  - Accomack-York, 1923 Sept-Dec. (Volume 28)
  - Accomack-York, 1924 Jan-Apr. (Volume 29)
  - Accomack-York, 1924 May-Aug. (Volume 30)
  - Accomack-York, 1924 Sept-Dec. (Volume 31)
  - Accomack-York, 1925 Jan-Mar. (Volume 32)
  - Accomack-York, 1925 Apr-June. (Volume 33)
  - Accomack-York, 1925 July-Dec. (Volume 34)
  - Accomack-York, 1926 Jan-June. (Volume 35)
  - Accomack-York, 1926 July-Dec. (Volume 36)
  - Accomack-York, 1927 Jan-June. (Volume 37)
  - Accomack-York, 1927 July-Dec. (Volume 38)
- Series III: Reports of Oyster Inspectors, 1898-1827 (APA 115)., Extent: 11 volumes.
  Reports of Oyster Inspectors, 1898-1927, consist of 11 volumes. These volumes contain summary statements of the total amount of fees, fines and taxes collected from the clam, crab, fish and oyster industries. The statements include the name of the inspector, district and county, date, and the amount and types of revenues collected. These volumes may also include information on the number of dredging boats and the number of acres of planting grounds assigned. Volume numbers were assigned at the time of processing.
  - Reports, 1898-1900. (Volume 1)
  - Reports, 1900-1902. (Volume 2)
  - Reports, 1900-1902. (Volume 3)
  - Reports, 1992-1903. (Volume 4)
  - Reports, 1902-1904. (Volume 5)
  - Reports, 1907-1910. (Volume 6)
  - Reports, 1910-1913. (Volume 7)
  - Reports, 1913-1916. (Volume 8)
  - Reports, 1916-1920. (Volume 9)
  - Reports, 1920-1925. (Volume 10)
  - Reports, 1925-1927. (Volume 11)